Guide to the Wijnpersse Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Wijnpersse family papers
1746-1822
GEN MSS 618
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12
(95 boxes)
The collection consists of ninety-five manuscript and printed volumes, in their original bindings, created and accumulated by four members of the Wijnpersse family, relating to their scholarly careers at the Universities of Utrecht, Leiden and Groningen. Included are the major works of Dionysius van de Wijnpersse on logic and metaphysics in various annotated editions, and writings related to them in manuscript form; the annotated books and manuscripts of Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse; several volumes of lecture notes by Dionysius van de Wijnpersse, Jr., and his thesis which was published in Leiden in 1822; and the thesis, published before 1815, of Cornelius Adrianus van de Wijnpersse.
Wijnpersse family
Wijnpersse, Dionysius van de, 1724-1808
Wijnpersse, Dionysius van de, 1799-1870
Wijnpersse, Samuel Johannes van de, 1759-1842
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Rudi Thoemmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Wijnpersse Family
Biographical notes drawn from The Dictionary of Seventeenth and Eighteenth-Century Dutch Philosophers (Bristol, England: Thoemmes Press, 2003), s.v. Dionysius van de Wijnpersse and Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse.
Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1724-1808)
Dionysius van de Wijnpersse, one of the most influential philosophers in The Netherlands during the second half of the eighteenth century, was born at Middelburg in 1724. He studied philosophy in Utrecht from 1741, and after 1747 he studied theology at Leiden University, attending lectures in the humanities and social sciences as well. After his studies, Van de Wijnpersse became a minister in 1749, and as soon as 1752, he was appointed Professor of Philosophy at Groningen. In the same year of his appointment, Groningen University made him Doctor of Theology h.c. In 1758-1759, he was Rector magnificus. In 1769, he was appointed in Leiden, where he taught metaphysics, ethics, and eventually philosophia experimentalis. Van de Wijnpersse's teaching left six theses and two frequently reprinted manuals to posterity.
Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse (1759-1842)
Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse was born in Groningen on 11 June 1759. He was the son of Dionysius van de Wijnpersse and Anna Diederica Thiens. He matriculated from Leiden in 1770 and 1775, and received his PhD in 1780. His life was divided between philosophy and theology. He was a Reformed minister in the villages of Nieuwveen (1782) amd IJsselmonde (1784) before being appointed as Professor of Philosophy at Groningen University. He left after two years to become a minister in Amsterdam, but was deposed in 1796 for refusing to sign a declaration of approval of the new political regime. In 1803, he was appointed as Professor extraordinarius of philosophy in Leiden. In 1822, he was granted his superannuation which he enjoyed until his death in Leiden on 22 November 1842.
Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1799-1870)
Dionysius van de Wijnpersse was the son of Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse.
Cornelius Adrianus van de Wijnpersse
Cornelius Adrianus van de Wijnpersse was either a cousin or brother of Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1799-1870).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of ninety-five manuscript and printed volumes, in their original bindings, created and accumulated by four members of the Wijnpersse family, relating to their scholarly careers at the Universities of Utrecht, Leiden and Groningen. Included are the major works of Dionysius van de Wijnpersse on logic and metaphysics in various annotated editions, and related writings in manuscript; the annotated books and manuscripts of Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse; several volumes of lecture notes by Dionysius van de Wijnpersse, Jr., and his thesis which was published in Leiden in 1822; and the thesis, published before 1815, of Cornelius Adrianus van de Wijnpersse.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I. Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1724-1808), 1746-1806; II. Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse (1759-1842), 1788-1821; III. Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1799-1870), 1812-1822; and IV. Other Papers and Unidentified Material, 1815.
Ethics; Logic; Metaphysics; Ontology; Philosophers -- Netherlands -- 18th century; Philosophers -- Netherlands -- 19th century; Philosophy and religion; Philosophy, Dutch -- 18th century; Philosophy, Dutch -- 19th century; Groningen (Netherlands); Leiden (Netherlands); Utrecht (Netherlands); Wijnpersse, Cornelius Adrianus van de; Wijnpersse, Dionysius van de, 1724-1808; Wijnpersse, Dionysius van de, 1799-1870; Wijnpersse, Samuel Johannes van de, 1759-1842; Rijksuniversiteit te Groningen; Rijksuniversiteit te Leiden; Rijksuniversiteit te Utrecht
- Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1724-1808), 1746-1806; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged into two subseries: Manuscript material and Printed material.
  - Manuscript material
    - Dictata Cl. van de Wynpersse in Metaphykiam Ontologia, undated (Box 1)
    - Dictata Clarissimi Professoris Leidensis D. van de Wynpersse [...] in primam Metaphysices [...] Insitutiones Ontologicas, 1776-77 (Box 2)
    - Dictata Clarissimi Professoris Leidensis D. van de Wynpersse [...] in secundum Metaphysices [...] Psychologiam, undated (Box 3)
    - Dictata Clarissimi Professoris Leidensis D. van de Wynpersse [...] in tertiam Metaphysices [...] Theologiam Naturalem, undated (Box 4)
    - Dictata Clarissimi Professoris Leidensis D. van de Wynpersse [...] in quartam Metaphysices [...] Cosmologicas Institutiones, undated (Box 5)
    - D. van de Wynpersse, Dictata in Metaphysicam, tom I, sive Dictata in Ontologiam, undated (Box 6)
    - D. v. d. Wynpersse, Dictata in Metaphysicam, tom II, sive Dictata in Psychologiam, undated (Box 7)
    - D. van de Wynpersse [...] Dictatore in Metaphysicam, tom III, Dictata in Theologiam Naturalem, 1777 (Box 8)
    - D. van de Wynpersse [...] Dictatorum in Metaphysicam, tom IV, Dictata in Cosmologiam, 1777 (Box 9)
    - Dictata ad Artem Logicam [vol. 1], undated (Box 10)
    - Dictata ad Artem Logicam [vol. 2], undated (Box 11)
    - Dictata ad Artem Logicam [vol. 1], undated (Box 12)
    - Dictata ad Artem Logicam [vol. 2], undated (Box 13)
    - Dictata ad Pufendorfium, tom I, undated (Box 14)
    - Dictata ad Pufendorfium [vol. 2], undated (Box 15)
    - Dictata ad Pufendorfium [vol. 3], undated (Box 16)
    - Dictata ad Pufendorfium [vol. 4], undated (Box 17)
    - Dictata ad Pufendorfium [vol. 5], undated (Box 18)
    - Dictata ad Pufendorfium [vol. 6], undated (Box 19)
    - Notae in Ill. Sam. Pufendorfi, undated (Box 20)
    - Notae in Ill. Sam. Pufendorfi [vol. 2], undated (Box 21)
    - Dictata in Astronomiam, dictatore in usum globum, undated (Box 22)
    - Dictata in Astronomiam, dictatore in cognitionem atque usum globorum, undated (Box 23)
  - Printed material
    - Specimen Philosophico-Morale de Libertinismo and five other titles (with manuscript interleavings and annotations), 1746 (Box 24)
    - Specimen Philosophico-Morale de Libertinismo and five other titles, 1746 (Box 25)
    - Specimen Philosophico-Morale de Libertinismo, 1746 (Box 26)
    - Oratio de Recentiorum Meritis, 1759 (Box 27)
    - Institutiones Metaphysicae in Usum Academicum, 1764 [1770 written above in manuscript] (Box 28)
    - Institutiones Metaphysicae in Usum Academicum, 1770 (Box 29)
    - Institutiones Metaphysicae in Usum Academicum, 1789 (Box 30)
    - Institutiones Logicae in Usum Academicum, 1767 (Box 31)
    - Institutiones Logicae in Usum Academicum, 1779 (Box 32)
    - Institutiones Logicae in Usum Academicum, 1806 (Box 33)
    - Onderwijs in de Redenkunde, ten dienste zijner, Academiesche Lessen, 1780 (Box 34)
    - Oratio de Recta Philautia, 1780 (Box 35)
    - Betoog der waare en eeuwige Godheid, van onzen heere Jesus Christus, 1794 (Box 36)
- Samuel Johannes van de Wijnpersse (1759-1842), 1788-1821; Series II
  - Manuscript material
    Scope and Contents
    Includes volumes of lecture notes.
    - Excerpta ex dictis S.J.v.d.Wijnpersse ad Institutiones Metaphysicas (Metaphysica, vol. 1), 1816-18 (Box 37)
    - Excerpta ex dictis S.J.v.d.Wijnpersse ad Theologiam Naturalem (Metaphysica, vol. 2), 1816-17 (Box 38)
    - Dictata in Philosophia, moralis, 1817-18 (Box 39)
    - Notae breviores ad Institutiones Religionis Naturalis (Notae), 1820-21 (Box 40)
    - Institutiones Religionis Naturalis (Comp.), 1820-21 (Box 41)
  - Printed material
    - Oratio Inauguralis, de Regimine Idearum Connexarum Prudenter Instituendo, 1788 (Box 42)
    - 'Nagelaaten Leerreedenen' by H.D. Portner; bound for S.J. van de Wijnpersse 1798, 1791, 1798 (Box 43)
    - Oratio Inauguralis de amore dei erga (1 of 2 copies), 1803 (Box 44)
    - Oratio Inauguralis de amore dei erga (2 of 2 copies), 1803 (Box 45)
    - Institutiones Philosophiae Moralis, in usum academicum (with manuscript interleavings and annotations), 1808 (Box 46)
    - Institutiones Philosophiae Moralis, in usum academicum, 1808 (Box 47)
- Dionysius van de Wijnpersse (1799-1870), 1812-1822; Series III
  - Manuscript material
    Volumes with like bindings have been grouped together and then arranged either alphabetically or chronologically.
    - Dictata in Anthropologiam (notes taken from lectures by S. J. Brugmans), 1818-19 (Box 48)
    - Dictata ad Antiquitates, Graecas (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1817-18 (Box 49)
    - Dictata in antiquitates Romanas (notes taken from lectures by A.D. Wyttenbach), 1815-16 (Box 50)
    - Dictata in historiam antiquam, media partem (notes taken from lectures by A.D. Wyttenbachii), 1815-16 (Box 51)
    - Dictata in historiam mediam et novum (notes taken from lectures by Wyttenbachii), 1816-17 (Box 52)
    - Dictata in historiam Philosophiae (notes taken from lectures by A.D. Wyttenbachii), 1816-17 (Box 53)
    - Dictata in Historiam Philosophia (notes taken from lectures by E.A. Borgeri), 1818-19 (Box 54)
    - Dictata in Aeschinis, orationem contra Ctesiphontem (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1818-19 (Box 55)
    - Dictata in Ciceronem de legibus (notes taken from lectures by A.D. Wyttenbachii), 1815-16 (Box 56)
    - Dictata in Ciceronem de officiis (notes taken from lectures by D. Wyttenbachii), 1815-17 (Box 57)
    - Dictata in Ciceronem de divinatione (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1817-18 (Box 58)
    - Dictata in Ciceronis oratorem (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1818-19 (Box 59)
    - Dictata in Demosthenem, vol. I (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1816[?] (Box 60)
    - Dictata in Demosthenam, vol. II (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1816[?] (Box 61)
    - Dictata in Homeri (notes taken from lectures by H. Tollius), 1815-16 (Box 62)
    - Dictata in Homeri (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1815-16 (Box 63)
    - Dictata in Homeri (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1816-17 (Box 64)
    - Dictata in Euripidis, Hecubam and Orestem (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1816-17 (Box 65)
    - Dictata in Plutarchi (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1816-1817 (Box 66)
    - Dictata in Sophoclis (notes taken from lectures by J. Bakii), 1817-18 (Box 67)
    - Dictata in Encyclopædiam et methodologiam juris universi (notes taken from lectures by A.H.G. Tydeman), 1817-18 (Box 68)
    - Dictata ad J.A. Bachii historiam juris (notes taken from lectures by H.A. Tydeman), 1817-18 (Box 69)
    - Dictata ad Institutiones Juris Rom (notes taken from lectures by H.A. Tydeman), 1817-18 (Box 70)
    - Dictata in Jus Criminale, secundum codicum Gallicum poenale (notes taken from lectures by J.M. Kemper), undated (Box 71)
    - Dictata in H[ugonis] Grotii opus de Jure Belli et Pacis (notes taken from lectures by J.M Kemper), undated (Box 72)
    - Dictata ad Jus Hodiernum, civile et criminale, [notes taken from lectures by N. Smallenburg], 1819-20 (Box 73)
    - Dictata in Jus Natura (notes taken from lectures by J.M. Kemper), 1818-20 (Box 74)
    - Dictata in Oeconomiam Politicum (notes taken from lectures by A.H.G. Tydeman), 1818-19 (Box 75)
    - Dictata ad Pandectus Justinianeas [Digest of Justinian] partem primum (notes taken from lectures by N. Smallenburg), 1818 (Box 76)
    - Dictata ad Pandectus Justinianeas [Digest of Justinian] partem secundum (notes taken from lectures by N. Smallenburg), 1818-19 (Box 77)
    - Dictata ad Pandectus Justinianeas [Digest of Justinian] partem quartum (notes taken from lectures by N. Smallenburg), 1819 (Box 78)
    - Ius Naturae apud Prof. S[eerp] Gratama, 1812 (Box 79)
    - Oratio de Viriatho [...] Lugduni Batavoriam in templo Gallicano a D .v. d. Wynpersse, 1815 (Box 80)
    - Historia Iuris Romani, 1816 (Box 81)
    - De Encyclopaedia Juris, 1817 (Box 82)
    - Ius Criminale, 1818 (Box 83)
    - Institutionum Liber I, undated (Box 84)
    - Institutionum Liber II, undated (Box 85)
    - Lib. XXV [de legibus], undated (Box 86)
    - Institutionum. Brevis Expositio [ad legem Romanum], undated (Box 87)
    - Ius Publicum, undated (Box 88)
  - Printed material
    - Disputatio Juridica Inauguralis, ad locum juris Romani, qui est de fideicommissis, sive de fideicommissorum Romanorum historia, 1822 (Box 89)
    - Dissertatio Literaria Inauguralis de Xenocrate Chalcedonio, Philosopho Academico, 1822 (Box 90)
- Other Papers and Unidentified Material, 1815, undated; Series IV
  - Manuscript material
    - Generale Remarques Wegens de Practyk (in Dutch), undated (Box 91)
    - Dictata in Philosophiam Practicam, Joh. Franc. Buddei ("D. Wynpers" given on spine), undated (Box 92)
    - Adversaria (index of terms, probably created by Dionysius van de Wijnpersse, Jr.), undated (Box 93)
    - Index Biographicus Virorum doctrina illustrium, praesertim aevi recentioris (Dionysius van de Wijnpersse, Jr.?), undated (Box 94)
  - Printed material
    - Specimen Medicum Inaugurale, exhibens animdaversiones atque observationes nonnullas medicas by Cornelius Adrianus van de Wijnpersse, 1815 (Box 95)